A Guide to the Papers of Paul B. Barringer, 1881-1983
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
A Guide to the Papers of Paul B. Barringer 1881-1983
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-34
1 box, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 0.5 linear feet, 47 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Biographical Information
Paul Brandon Barringer was born in western North Carolina on February 13, 1857. He entered the University of Virginia as a student in 1875, received his medical degree in 1877, and earned his supplemental degree of doctor of medicine from the University of New York the following year. After graduation he practiced medicine in Gaston County, North Carolina for several years and then went on his "Grand Tour" to Europe in 1981. While there he visited medical centers in London, Edinburgh, Dublin, Paris, and Vienna. Returning to the United States in 1882, he settled in Charlotte, North Carolina, married, and practiced medicine. In 1886 he accepted a position as resident physician at Davidson College, a college founded by his maternal grandfather, Robert Hall Morrison. He founded his own "Preparatory School for Medical Students," giving courses in anatomy, histology, physiology, and biology.
In 1889 he was asked to succeed Dr. James Cabell as Professor of Physiology and Surgery at the University of Virginia; he held this position until 1907. He was Chairman of the Faculty from 1896 to 1903, and labored unceasingly for the construction of a University Hospital and for the development of clinical facilities for the School of Medicine. When the first unit of the University Hospital opened in 1901, Dr. Barringer became its superintendent. He was also instrumental in directing the addition of the Hospital's South Wing in 1905 and the North Wing in 1907. In 1907 he left the University to become President of Virginia Polytechnic Institute where he remained until his retirement in 1912.
The Barringer House in Charlottesville was built in 1894 and moved into by the Barringer family in 1897. It exemplifies the Queen Anne architecture popularized during the late nineteenth century while also reflecting High Gothic Victorian influences. Located close to the medical school, Barringer encouraged medical students to visit his home frequently and they willingly did. Avoiding proposed demolition in the early 1980s, the house was restored and became the French House for the University in 1986.
Both a writer and a teacher, Dr. Barringer authored a standard text on physiology and published papers on syphilis, cholera, typhoid fever, and poisonous reptiles. He was especially interested in preventive medicine and public health. Dr. Barringer was a member of the Raven Society; elected honorary president of the University of Virginia Alumni Association; and a president of the Medical Society of Virginia, an organization in which he was a member for 50 years. The Barringer Wing of the University of Virginia Hospital is named after him. He died on January 9, 1941, in Charlottesville.
Scope and Content
The collection includes letters written to his parents in 1881 and 1882 while Dr. Barringer was traveling in Europe; a paper he wrote on death; a chapter in German from his memoir, "The Natural Bent;" other biographical material; and newspaper clippings regarding a proposed demolition of his home in 1983.
Arrangement
The box is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Letter from Paul B. Barringer to his mother 1881 April 21, 1 ALS 8pp., 1 TD 3pp. (Box-folder 01-001)
  Letter written in Paris.
- Letter from Paul B. Barringer to his mother 1881 September 9, 1 ALS 12pp., 1 TD 6pp. (Box-folder 01-002)
  Letter written in Vienna.
- Letter from Paul B. Barringer to his father 1881 September 24, 1 ALS 4pp., 1 TD 2pp. (Box-folder 01-003)
- Letter from Paul B. Barringer to his father 1881 October 18, 1 ALS 12pp., 1 TD 6pp. (Box-folder 01-004)
- Letter from Paul B. Barringer to his father 1881 November 7, 1 ALS 10pp., 1 TD 7pp. (Box-folder 01-005)
- Letter from Paul B. Barringer to his father 1881 November 16, 1 ALS 7pp., 1 TD 5pp. (Box-folder 01-006)
- Letter from Paul B. Barringer to his mother 1881 January 4, 1 ALS 7pp., 1 TD 5pp. (Box-folder 01-007)
- Letter from Paul B. Barringer to his father 1881 [1882] January 14, 1 ALS 2pp., 1 TD 1p. (Box-folder 01-008)
- "Virginia Medical Monthly": Obituary Record: Dr. Paul Brandon Barringer 1941 February, 1 TD photocopy 2pp. (Box-folder 01-009)
- "Virginia Medical Monthly": Resolutions on Dr. Barringer [1941] April, 1 TD photocopy 1p. (Box-folder 01-010)
- Victor Clay Barringer note 1956, 1 AN 1p. (Box-folder 01-011)
- "UVa Medical Alumni Association News Letter": Dr. Barringer's Diplomas Presented to Medical Library 1969 May June, 1 carbon TD 2pp. (Box-folder 01-012)
  galley proof for publication
- Dr. Paul B. Barringer (1857-1941), A Biographical Sketch by Dr. W. Moll 1977 June 22, 1 TD 11pp. (Box-folder 01-013)
  Contains information taken mostly from Dr. Barringer's memoirs which were complied by his daughter Anna and published under the title "The Natural Bent."
- Articles regarding the proposed demolition of the Barringer house 1983, 3 newspaper clippings 5 pp., 3 photocopies of the clippings 5 pp. (Box-folder 01-014)
- Activities reports n.d., 15 magnetic cards in 3 folders (Box-folder 01-015)
  These are placed in the Barringer collection because they were filed with his papers, and the letters from Barringer to his parents were also on magnetic cards.
- Ein Medizinstudent in Wien, 1881 n.d., 1 TD 17pp. (Box-folder 01-016)
  This is chapter 33 in German from "The Natural Bent" by Paul B. Barringer.
- "Our Old Friend Death" by Paul B. Barringer n.d., 1 carbon TD 11pp. (Box-folder 01-017)